<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Case of using or forbearing the establish'd liturgie, during the late troublesome times, and prohibition of it by the then usurpers.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1191A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173505</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47682815</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47682815</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172774</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78280)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172774)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2649:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Case of using or forbearing the establish'd liturgie, during the late troublesome times, and prohibition of it by the then usurpers.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Year MDCLXXII [1672]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Eton College. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172774:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF USING or FORBEARING The Eſtabliſh'd LITURGIE, During the late troubleſome times, and Prohibition of it by the then Uſurpers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:172774:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172774:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>IF this ſhort Diſcourſe needed any <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendatory Letters,</hi> beſide what its own intrinſick worth doth abundantly afford, it might readily fetch them from the <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of its <hi>Author,</hi> (if others, as well as my ſelf, ben't much miſtaken,) and from its <hi>own ſuitableneſs</hi> to our <hi>preſent Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For its <hi>Author;</hi> There wanted not high probabilities to perſwade, the prefixing of the Reverend Name, of as <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Judicious</hi> a <hi>Prelate,</hi> as perhaps any that in our dayes have adorn'd the <hi>Engliſh Church:</hi> But it was not thought expedient to be guilty, though but in appearance, either of doing any Injury to the memory of that Excellent Perſon, or of impoſing upon the World. The knowing <hi>Reader</hi> may therefore pleaſe to uſe his own Judgement on ſeveral paſſages that he will find herein, and eſpecially on the Reſemblance which it wears to the other worthy works of that <q rend="inline">ſtayd and well weigh'd man, who conceiv'd all things deliberately, dwelt upon them diſcreetly, diſcern'd things that differ exactly, paſs'd
<pb facs="tcp:172774:3"/>his Judgement rationally, and expreſs'd it aptly, clearly and honeſtly.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For its <hi>ſuitableneſs</hi> to our <hi>preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition;</hi> It will appear to any, that ſhall conſider the weighty <hi>Subjects</hi> herein treated of, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Obligation of Humane Laws, Scandal, Schiſm,</hi> &amp;c. apply'd particularly to our <hi>Eſtabliſh'd Liturgie:</hi> and compare them with that <hi>Juncture of Affairs at this time,</hi> wherein all ſorts of men do ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally interest themſelves.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Uſefulneſs</hi> of this Tractate, chiefly on the account laſt mention'd, may, 'tis hop'd, be a ſufficient <hi>Apology,</hi> for preſuming to take the ſame liberty in this, which others have taken formerly, in caſes of a more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, and therefore leſs profitable concern: Eſpecially ſeeing that even this alſo was in a ſort publiſh'd before; having been for divers years, among the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of my Own, and ſeveral others Studyes, that I know, and I have reaſon to believe of more whom I know not: and that beſides, there was danger of a worſe Impreſſion; ſince the printing ſome of the contents hereof (as is ſuppos'd,) in <hi>The Obligation of Humane Laws,</hi> diſcuſſed by <hi>I. H.</hi> had cauſed divers <hi>Bookſellers</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172774:3"/>
            <head>THE CASE OF USING or FORBEARING The Eſtabliſh'd LITURGIE, During the late troubleſome times, and Prohibition of it by the then Uſurpers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas you are deſirous to know what my <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Practiſe</hi> is, concerning <hi>the uſing or forbearing of the eſtabliſh'd Liturgie, (either in whole or in part,) in the publick ſervice of God, and offices of the Church:</hi> If that may be any ſatisfaction to your ſelf or Friends, I ſhall fully acquaint you with what my <hi>practiſe</hi> is, (whereunto if my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172774:4"/>
               <hi>jugment</hi> be not conform'd, I am then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably my own condemner;) And upon what conſiderations I have, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the variation of times, varied my ſelf therein.</p>
            <p>So long as my Congregation continued unmixt with Souldiers, (as well after, as before, the promulgation of the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of the two Houſes, for the aboliſhing of Common-Prayer) I continued the uſe of it, as I had ever formerly done, in the moſt peaceable and orderly times, not omitting thoſe very Prayers, the ſilencing of which I could not but know to have been chiefly aimed at in the <hi>Ordinance; viz,</hi> thoſe for the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Queen</hi> and the <hi>Biſhops:</hi> And ſo I did alſo, though ſome Souldiers were caſually preſent, till ſuch time as a whole Troop coming to Quarter in the Town (with a purpoſe to continue a kind of Garriſon or Head-Quarters amongſt us,) were ſo enraged at my reading of it the firſt Sunday after they came, that immediately after morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Service was ended, they ſeized on the Book, and tore it all to pieces.</p>
            <p>Thence forward, during their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance here, for full ſix months and upwards,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172774:4"/>
               <hi>viz.</hi> From the beginning of <hi>November,</hi> till they were called away to <hi>Naſeby</hi> Fight in <hi>May</hi> following; beſides that for want of a Book, of neceſſity I muſt; I ſaw that it behoved me alſo for the preventing of further outrages, to wave the uſe of the Book, for the time at leaſt, in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Services: Only I read the <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> with the <hi>Verſicles,</hi> and <hi>Pſalm</hi> for the day; Then, after the firſt Leſſon in the Fore-noon, <hi>Benedictus,</hi> or <hi>Jubilate;</hi> And in the After-noon, <hi>Cantate;</hi> After the ſecond Leſſon alſo in the Fore-noon, ſometimes the <hi>Creed,</hi> ſometimes the ten <hi>Commandements;</hi> and ſometimes nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but only ſang a <hi>Pſalm</hi> and ſo to Sermon. But all that while in the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Sacraments, the Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation of Matrimonie, Burial of the Dead, and Churching of Women, I conſtantly uſed the ancient Forms and Rites, to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them reſpectively belonging, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the appointment in the Book: Only I was careful to make Choice of ſuch times and opportunities, as I might do them with moſt ſecrecy, and without diſturbance of the Souldiers: But at the Celebration of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> I was the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172774:5"/>more ſecure to do it publickly, becauſe I was aſſured none of the Souldiers would be preſent.</p>
            <p>After their departure; I took the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to uſe, either the whole Liturgie, or but ſome part of it; omitting ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more, ſometimes leſs, upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as I judged it moſt expedient in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the Auditory; eſpecially if any Souldiers or other unknown perſons happened to be preſent: But all the while, the ſubſtance of what I omitted, I contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into my Prayer before Sermon, the Phraſe and Order only varied; which yet I endeavoured to temper in ſuch ſort, as any perſon of ordinary capacity, might eaſily perceive what my meaning was, and yet the words as little left open to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception or cavil as might be.</p>
            <p>About two years ago I was advertiſed (but in a very friendly manner, by a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament man of note in theſe parts,) that at a publick meeting in <hi>G.</hi> great complaint was made by ſome Miniſters (of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Gang, as I afterwards found) of my refractorineſs to obey the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Order in that behalf; The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man told me withall, that although they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172774:5"/>knew long before what my Judgment and Practice was, yet they were not forward to take notice of it, before complaint made; which being now done in ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick manner, if they ſhould not take knowledge of it, the blame would lie upon them. He therefore adviſed me to conſider well what I had to do; For I muſt reſolve either to adventure the loſs of my Living, or to lay aſide <hi>Common-Prayer;</hi> which if I ſhould continue after complaint and admonition, it would not be in his power, nor in the power of any friend I had, to preſerve me.</p>
            <p>The effect of my then-Anſwer was that if the caſe were ſo, the deliberation was not hard, I having long ago conſidered of the caſe, and reſolv'd what I might with a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> do, and what were fitteſt for me <hi>in prudence</hi> to do if I ſhould ever be put to it, <hi>viz. To forbear the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Common-Prayer-Book ſo far as might ſatisfie the letter of the Ordinance rather then forſake my Station.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My next buſineſs then was, to bethink my ſelf of ſuch a courſe, to be thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth held in the publick worſhip in my own Pariſh, as might be likelieſt neither
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172774:6"/>to bring danger to my ſelf by the uſe, nor to bring ſcandal to my Brethren by the diſuſe of the eſtabliſht Liturgie: And the courſe was this; to which I have held me ever ſince.</p>
            <p>I begin the Service with a Preface of Scripture, and an Exhortation inferr'd thence to make confeſſion of ſins; which Exhortation I have framed out of the <hi>Exhortation</hi> and <hi>Abſolution</hi> in the Book, contracted and put together, and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the moſt part in the very ſame words and phraſes, but purpoſely here and there transplaced, that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear <hi>not to be,</hi> and <hi>yet to be</hi> the ſame. Then follows the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> it ſelf, in the ſame order it was, only with the addition of ſome words, whereby it's rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained then altered; the whole form whereof, both for your fuller ſatisfaction in that particular, and that you may partly conjecture what manner of addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or change I have made proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hereunto (yet none ſo large,) in other parts of the holy Office, I have here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwritten.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:172774:6"/>
            <p>OAlmighty God and merciful Father, We thy unworthy ſervants do with ſhame and ſorrow confeſs, that we have all our life long gone aſtray out of thy wayes, like loſt ſheep; and that, by following too much the vain devices and deſires of our own Hearts, we have grievouſly offended againſt thy holy Laws, both in thought word and deed: We have many times left undone thoſe good duties, which we might and ought to have done; and we have many times done thoſe evils, when we might have avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them, which we ought not to have done. We confeſs O Lord, that there is no health at all in us, nor help in any creature to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve us; but all our hope is in thy mercy, whoſe juſtice by our ſins we have ſo far pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked. Have mercy upon us therefore O Lord, Have mercy upon us, miſerable offenders; Spare us good Lord, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs our faults, that we periſh not; But ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy gracious promiſes, declared unto mankind, in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, Reſtore us upon our true repentance into thy grace and favour: And grant O most mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father for his ſake, that we henceforth ſtudy to ſerve and pleaſe thee, by leading a godly righteous and ſober life, to the glory
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172774:7"/>of thy holy name, and the eternal comfort of our own ſouls, through Jeſus Christ our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this Confeſſion, the Lords Prayer, with the <hi>Verſicles</hi> and <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> and then the <hi>Pſalms</hi> for the day, and then the firſt Leſſon: After which in the Fore-noon ſometimes <hi>Te Deum,</hi> (but then only when I think the Auditory will bear it;) and ſometimes an <hi>Hymn</hi> of my own compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, gathered out of the Pſalms; the Church <hi>Collects,</hi> and a general form of <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi> (which I did the rather becauſe ſome have noted the want of ſuch a form, as the only thing wherein our Liturgie ſeemed to be defective;) And in the After-noon, after the firſt Leſſon, the 98 or 67 Pſalm; then the ſecond Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, with <hi>Benedictus</hi> or <hi>Jubilate</hi> after it. In the Fore-noon and in the After-noon a ſinging <hi>Pſalm,</hi> then followeth the <hi>Creed,</hi> with <hi>Dominus vobiſcum,</hi> and ſometimes the <hi>Verſicles</hi> in the end of the <hi>Letany,</hi> [<hi>From our enemies defend us O Christ,</hi> &amp;c.] if I like my Auditory, otherwiſe I omit the <hi>Verſicles.</hi> After the <hi>Creed,</hi> &amp;c. inſtead of the <hi>Letany,</hi> and other Prayers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172774:7"/>in the Book, I have taken the ſubſtance of the Prayer, I was wont to uſe before Sermon, and diſpoſed it into ſeveral Collects or Prayers, ſome longer ſome ſhorter, but new-modell'd into the language of the Common Prayer Book, much more then it was before; and in the Pulpit, before Sermon, I uſe only a ſhort Prayer in reference to the hearing of the Word, and no more: So that upon the matter, in theſe Prayers, I do but the ſame thing I did before; ſave only that what before I ſpake without Book, and in a continued form, and in the Pulpit, I now read, and in a written Book, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into parcels; and in the Reading Desk or Pew. Between which Prayers and the ſinging Pſalm before Sermon I do daily uſe one other Collect; of which ſort I have for the purpoſe compoſed ſundry, made up, as the former, for the moſt part out of the Church-Collects, <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventual, Quadrageſimal, Paſchal,</hi> and <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſtal</hi> for their proper Seaſons: And at other times Collects of a more general nature, as for Pardon, Repentance, Grace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And after one or more of them, in the Fore-noon, I uſually repeat
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172774:8"/>the ten <hi>Commandements,</hi> with a ſhort <hi>Collect</hi> after, for Grace to enable us to keep them.</p>
            <p>This hath been my <hi>Practiſe,</hi> and is like ſtill to be, unleſs ſome happy change of Affairs reſtore us the liberty of uſing the old way again, or it be made appear to my underſtanding, by ſome able chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Friend, that I have therein done otherwiſe then I ought to have done. For I may ſay truly that I have not yet met with any thing, in diſcourſe either with my own Reaſon or with others, of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ſtrength to convince me, that I have herein done any thing but what may ſtand with the Principles as well of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſimplicity as prudence.</p>
            <p>There are but three things that I know of (that are of any conſideration) op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>The Obligation of the LAWS.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>The SCANDAL of the Example.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>An unſeemly ſymbolizing (at leaſt) with Schiſmaticks, if not a partaking with them in the SCHISM.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:172774:8"/>
               <head>1 LAW. Object. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt and ſtrongeſt</hi> Objection, <hi>(which I ſhall therefore propoſe to the most advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Objectors) is that which is grounded upon the LAWS, and their</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, <hi>For it may be objected,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 That an Humane Law rightly eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, ſo long as it continueth a Law, obligeth the Subject (and that for Conſcience ſake) to the obſervation thereof, in ſuch manner and form as in the ſaid Law is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and according to the true meaning and intention of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver therein.</p>
               <p>2 That a Law is then underſtood to be rightly eſtabliſhed, when it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth nothing but what is honeſt and lawfull, and is enacted by ſuch perſon or perſons as have full and ſufficient Authority to make Laws.</p>
               <p>3. That a Law ſo eſtabliſhed, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth a Law, and is in force till it be either repealed by as good and full Authority, as that by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172774:9"/>which it was made, or elſe anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quated by a long continued (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enforced) diſuſe, with the tacite preſumed conſent of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver.</p>
               <p>4 That the Act printed before the Common Prayer Book, and enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled [<hi>An Act for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of,</hi> &amp;c.] was ſuch a Law: being it was eſtabliſhed in a Full and Free Parliament, and in peaceable times, and ratified by the Royal Aſſent.</p>
               <p>5 That it ſtill continueth in force; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not yet repealed, but by ſuch perſons, as (at leaſt in the opinion of thoſe that maintain the diſpute) for want of the Royal Aſſent, have not a ſufficient Right or Authority to do ſuch an Act: nor diſuſed, but of late time, and that by enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and (as is preſumed) much againſt the Mind and Will of the Law-giver.</p>
               <p>6 That therefore it ſtill reteineth the power of obliging in point of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: That power being ſo eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential and intrinſecal to every
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172774:9"/>Law, <hi>quatenus</hi> a <hi>Law,</hi> that it can in no wiſe be ſeparated from it.</p>
               <p>7 And that therefore no Miniſter pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly officiating in the Church can with a good Conſcience, either omit any part of that which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the aforeſaid Law; or uſe any other form then what is conteined in the aforeſaid Book: But muſt either uſe the form pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Book, or elſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to officiate.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Anſwer</hi> to this <hi>Objection,</hi> (granting all in the Premiſes beſides) dependeth upon the right underſtanding of that which is affirmed concerning the <hi>obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Laws, according to the intention of the Law-giver.</hi> Which if it ſhould be underſtood preciſely, of that <hi>particular actual</hi> and <hi>immediate intention,</hi> which the Law-giver had in making of any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Law, and <hi>is ſufficiently declared by the words of the Law,</hi> will not hold true in all caſes. But there is ſuppoſed beſides that, in the Law-giver, a more <hi>general habitual</hi> and <hi>ultimate intention,</hi> of a more excellent and tranſcendent nature then
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172774:10"/>the Former, which is to have an influence into, and over-ruling power over all particular Laws; viz. <hi>An intention by the Laws to procure and promote the publick good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The former intention bindeth, where it is ſubſervient to the Letter, or conſiſtent with it; and conſequently bindeth in ordinary caſes, or elſe the Law is not an wholeſome Law. But where the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Law by reaſon of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture of circumſtances or iniquity of the times (contingencies which no Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver could either certainly fore-ſee, or, if fore-ſeen, ſufficiently provide againſt) would rather be prejudicial then advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to the publick, or is manifeſtly attended with ſuch inconveniences and grievous conſequents to the obſervers, as all the imaginable good that can redound to the publick thereby, cannot in any reaſonable meaſure countervail; in ſuch caſe the Law obligeth not, but according to the latter and more general intention only. Even as in the operations of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, particular agents do ordinarily move according to their proper and particular inclinations: Yet upon ſome occaſions and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172774:10"/>to ſerve the ends and intentions of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Nature (for the avoiding of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which Nature abhors) they are ſometimes carried with motions quite contrary to their particular Natures: as the Air to deſcend, and the Water to aſcend, for the avoiding of vacuity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The common received <hi>Maxime</hi> (which hath been ſufficiently miſapplied, and that ſometimes to evil purpoſes, ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of theſe unhappy diviſions) in the true meaning of it looketh this way; <hi>Salus populi ſuprema lex.</hi> The equity of which <hi>Maxime,</hi> as it leaveth in the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver</hi> a power of diſpenſing with the Law (which is a ſuſpenſion of the obligation thereof for the time, in reſpect of the proper and particular intention) as he ſhall ſee it expedient in order to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good: So it leaveth in the <hi>Subject</hi> a liberty upon juſt occaſions (as in caſes of great exigency, and for the preventing of ſuch hazards and inconveniences as might prove of noiſome conſequence to the publick) to do otherwiſe then the Law requireth. And neither is the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of that power in the Law-giver, to be thought an unreaſonable prerogative, nor the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172774:11"/>uſe of this liberty in the Subject, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable preſumption: In as much as the power of diſpenſing with particular Laws is ſuch a prerogative, as without which no Common-wealth can be well governed, but Juſtice would be turned into Gall and Wormwood; nor can the Supreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, without forfeiture of that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs which he ows to the publick Weal, diveſt himſelf thereof. And he that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth of the Law-givers conſent to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with him for the obſerving of the Law, in ſuch needfull caſes (where he hath not the opportunity to conſult his pleaſure therein) preſumeth no more then he hath reaſon to do: For it may well be preſumed that the Law-giver, who is bound in all his Laws to intend the ſafety of the publick, and of every memeber thereof in his due proportion; hath no intention by the ſtrict obſervation of any particular Law to oblige any who is a member of the publick to his deſtruction or ruine, when the common good is not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably promoted thereby. Upon which ground it is generally reſolved by Caſuiſts, that <hi>No Conſtitution (meerly humane) can lay ſuch obligation upon the Conſcience of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172774:11"/>the Subject, but that he may (according to exigence of Circumſtances) do otherwiſe then the Conſtitution requires; provided it be done</hi> extra caſum ſcandali et con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptus, <hi>that is to ſay, Without either betraying in himſelf any contempt of the authority the Law-giver by his carriage, or giving any juſt occaſion of ſcandal to others by his example in ſo doing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have been ſomewhat the larger in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining this point, not only for the better clearing of the preſent doubt, but alſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the uſefulneſs of this conſideration, for the preventing and removing of many ſcruples that may happen to conſciencious men in ſuch times as theſe, wherein ſo many things are (and are like to be) commanded and forbidden, contrary to the eſtabliſhed Laws, and thoſe (as they are perſwaded) yet ſtanding in force. The beſt Rule that I know, to guide men in their deliberations and actions in ſuch emergent caſes (according to what hath been already delivered) is advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly and impartially to weigh the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and Inconveniencies as well on the one ſide as on the other, and then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them the one with the other, as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172774:12"/>they ſtand in relation to the publick good. And if after ſuch examination and compariſon made, it ſhall then evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently (or but in judgment of probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity) appear, that the obſervation of the Law, according to the proper inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law-giver therein, though with hazard of Eſtate, Liberty or ever Life it ſelf, hath a greater tendency to the publick good, and the preſervation of Church or Common-wealth in Safety Peace and Order, then the preventing of the aforeſaid hazards or other evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents, by doing otherwiſe then the Law requireth, can have: Or (which cometh to one) if the violating of the Law ſhall then appear to be more preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the publick good, then the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Subjects Eſtate, Liberty or Life, can be beneficial thereunto. In ſuch caſe, the Subject is bound to hazard all he hath, and to undergo whatſoever inconveniences or calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties can enſue thereupon, rather the violate the Law, with contempt of that Authority to which he oweth ſubjection. But if it ſhall, after ſuch compariſon made evidently (or but more probably then
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172774:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>the contrary) appear, that the preſervation of ſuch a perſons Life Liberty or Eſtate, would more benefit the Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, then the punctual obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law, at that time, and with thoſe circumſtances, would do: It were an unſeaſonable, unreaſonable and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſcrupuloſity, for ſuch a perſon to think himſelf in that caſe obliged, for the obſerving of the Law (perhaps but once or twice) with little or no benefit to the publick, to ruine himſelf, whereby to render himſelf unuſefull and unſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the publick ever after.</p>
               <p>To bring this diſcourſe home, and to apply it to the buſineſs now under diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute: Suppoſe we, ten, twenty, or an hundred <hi>godly Miniſters,</hi> well affected to the eſtabliſhed <hi>Liturgie,</hi> and actually poſſeſſed of <hi>Benefices</hi> with charge of Souls to them belonging, ſhould think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in conſcience obliged to uſe the <hi>whole</hi> form of the Book, as is by the firſt appointed, without any addition, omiſſion or alteration whatſoever, and ſhould not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the preſent conjuncture of Affairs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>reſolve to uſe the ſame accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly; it would be well conſidered, what
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172774:13"/>the effects and conſequents thereof would be. Beſides other evils theſe three are viſible, which muſt all unavoidably fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, one upon another, if any body ſhall be found (as doubtleſs within a ſhort time there will be found ſome or other) to inform and proſecute againſt them.</p>
               <p>1 The utter undoing of ſo many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy perſons, fit to do God and his Church ſervice, together with all thoſe other perſons that depend upon them for livelihood; by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the fruits of their Benefices whereby they ſhould buy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Bread, under Sequeſtration.</p>
               <p>2 The depriving thoſe perſons of the opportunities of diſcharging the Duties that belong unto them in their Miniſterial Calling; in not permitting them after ſuch Sequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, to teach or inſtruct the people belonging to their Charge or to exerciſe any thing of their Function publickly in the Church.</p>
               <p>3 The delivering over the Sheep of Chriſt, that lately were under the hands of faithful Shepherds, into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172774:13"/>the cuſtody of ravening Wolves; when ſuch Guides ſhall be over the ſeveral Congregations, as will be ſure to miſ-teach them one way or other: <hi>viz.</hi> either by inſtilling into them <hi>Puritanical</hi> and <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> Principles, that they may the more ſecurely exerciſe their <hi>Presbyterian</hi> tyranny over their Judgements, Conſciences, Perſons, and Eſtates: Or elſe by ſetting up new Lights before them, to lead them into a maze of <hi>Anabaptiſtical</hi> Confuſion and Frenſie.</p>
               <p>Theſe Conſequents are ſo heavie to the Sufferers, ſo certain to enſue upon the uſe of Common Prayer; and ſo much without the power of the Law-givers (in this ſtate of Affairs,) either to remedie or prevent: That it is beyond the wit of man to imagine, what benefit to the publick can accrue by the ſtrict obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Act, that may in any propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion countervail theſe miſchiefs. In which caſe, that man muſt needs ſuppoſe a ſtrange auſterity in the Law-giver, that dares not preſume of his conſent, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oblige
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172774:14"/>him (for the time) from obſerving the ſame.</p>
               <p>It would be alſo well conſidered, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he, that by his over-nice ſcrupulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity runneth all theſe hazards, be not (in ſome meaſure) guilty of his own undoing, deſerting his Station and betraying his Flock: and do not thereby loſe much of that comfort, which a Chriſtian Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour may take in his ſufferings, when they are laid upon him by the hand of God, and not pulled upon himſelf with his own hands. And more I ſhall not need to ſay as to that firſt <hi>Objection.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2</hi> SCANDAL. Object. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The next thing Objected is, The dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the SCANDAL, that others might be ready to take at the example: Who ſeeing the Law ſo little regarded by ſuch men (men that have Cure of Souls, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps alſo of ſome eminencie and eſteem in the Church, and whoſe Example will be much look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) will be eaſily encouraged by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172774:14"/>their Example, to ſet light by all Authority, and to take the liberty to obey and diſobey the Laws of their Soveraigns at their pleaſure.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>Objection</hi> after we are once well ſatisfied concerning the former, need not much trouble us. For</p>
               <p>1 Firſt, It ſeemeth a very unreaſonable thing, in caſes of great exigency (ſuch as we now ſuppoſe) that the fear of ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing our weak Brethren (which is but <hi>Debitum charitatis</hi> only) ſhould lay upon us a peremptory neceſſity of obſerving the Law punctually, whatſoever inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences or miſchiefs may enſue thereupon: Whereas the duty of obedience to our known Governours (which is <hi>Debitum juſtitiae</hi> alſo, and therefore more obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory then the other) doth not impoſe upon us that neceſſity; as hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewn.</p>
               <p>2. Beſides, Arguments drawn from <hi>Scandal,</hi> in things neither unlawful, nor (ſetting the reaſon of Scandal aſide) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expedient; as they are ſubject to ſundry frailties otherwiſe, ſo are they manifeſtly of no weight at all, when they are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoiſed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172774:15"/>with the apparent danger of evil conſequents on the other ſide. For in ſuch caſes there is commonly equall danger (if not rather ſometimes more) of Scandal to be taken from the Example the quite contrary way. We may ſee it in debating the point now in hand. It is alledged on the one ſide, that by laying aſide the uſe of Common Prayer, men that are not over-ſcrupulous will be encouraged to take a greater liberty in diſpenſing with the Laws (to the deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſing both of Laws and Governours) then they ought. And why may it not by the ſame reaſon be as well alledged on the other ſide, that by holding up a neceſſity of uſing Common Prayer, men that have tenderer Conſciences may be induced to entertain Scruples (to their own undoing, and the deſtruction of their people) when they need not?</p>
               <p>3 But that in the third place, which cometh up home to the buſineſs, and taketh off the Objection clearly, is this That in judging caſes of Scandal, we are not to look ſo much at the event, what it is or may be, as at the <hi>Cauſe</hi> whence it cometh. For ſometimes there is given
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172774:15"/>juſt cauſe of Scandal, and yet no Scandal followeth, becauſe it is not taken: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Scandal is taken, and yet no juſt cauſe given: And ſometimes there is both cauſe of Scandal given, and Scandal thereat taken. But no man is concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in any Scandal that happeneth to another, by occaſion of any thing done by him, neither is chargeable with it, farther then he is guilty of having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it.</p>
               <p>If then we give Scandal to others, and they take it not, the whole guilt is ours; they are faultleſs.</p>
               <p>If we give it and they take it, we are to bear a ſhare in the blame as well as they; and that a deeper ſhare too; <hi>(Vae homini: Wo to the man by whom the offence cometh,</hi> Matt. 18.7.) But if they take offence when we give none, it is a thing we cannot help, and therefore the whole blame muſt lie upon them. Wherefore, if at any time, any doubt ſhall ariſe in the caſe of Scandal, how far forth the danger thereof may or may not oblige us to the doing or not doing of any thing propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: The reſolution will come on much the eaſier, if we ſhall but rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172774:16"/>what it is to <hi>give Scandal,</hi> or how many wayes a man may become guilty of ſcandalizing another by his Example.</p>
               <p>The wayes as I conceive are but theſe four.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The firſt is, when a man doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before another man, which is in it ſelf evil, unlawfull, and ſinfull. In which caſe, neither the the intention of him that doth it, nor the event as to him that ſeeth it done, is of any conſideration. For it mattereth not whether the doer hath an intention to draw the other into Sin thereby or not; neither doth it matter whether the other were thereby induced to commit Sin or not. The very matter and ſubſtance of the action being evil, and done before others, is ſufficient to render the Doer guilty of having <hi>given Scandal;</hi> though neither he had any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention himſelf ſo to do, nor was any other perſon actually ſcandalized thereby. Becauſe whatſoever is in it ſelf, and in its <hi>own nature evil,</hi> is alſo of it ſelf and in its <hi>own nature ſcandalous</hi> and of ill example. Thus did <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phineas</hi> the Sons of <hi>Eli,</hi> give Scandal by their wretched profaneneſs and greedineſs about the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172774:16"/>of the Lord, and their vile and ſhameleſs abuſing the women, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.17.22. And ſo did <hi>David</hi> alſo give great Scandal in the matter of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.14. Here the Rule is, <hi>Do nothing that is evil, for fear of giving Scandal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſecond way is, when a man doth ſomething before another, with a direct intention and formal purpoſe of drawing him thereby to commit Sin. In which caſe, neither the matter of the Action, nor the Event is of any conſideration. For it maketh no difference (as to the Sin of giving Scandal) whether any man be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually enticed thereby to commit Sin or not: neither doth it make any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, whether the thing done, were in it ſelf unlawful or not; ſo as it had but an appearance of evil, and from thence an aptitude to draw another to the doing of that (by imitation) which would be really and intrinſecally evil. The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed intention alone (whatſoever the effect ſhould be, or what means ſoever ſhould be uſed to promote it) ſufficeth to induce the guilt of <hi>giving Scandal</hi> upon the Doer. This was <hi>Jeroboam's</hi> Sin, in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up the Calves with a formal purpoſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172774:17"/>and intention thereby (for his own ſecular and ambitious ends) to corrupt the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Religion, and to draw the people to an idolatrous worſhip: For which cauſe he is ſo often ſtigmatized with it, as with a note of infamie, to ſtick by him whilſt the world laſteth; being ſcarce ever mentioned in the Scripture, but with this addition, <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the Son of <hi>Nebat,</hi> that made <hi>Iſrael to ſin.</hi> Here the Rule is, <hi>Do nothing, good or evil, with an intention to give Scandal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 The third way is, when a man doth ſomething before another, which in it ſelf is not evil, but indifferent, and ſo according to the Rule of Chriſtian liberty lawful for him to do or not to do, as he ſhall ſee cauſe, (yea and perhaps other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe commodious and convenient for him to do;) yet whereat he probably fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeth the other will take Scandal, and be occaſioned thereby to do evil. In ſuch caſe, if the thing be not in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree <hi>(prudentially)</hi> neceſſary for him to do; but that he might, without very great inconvenience or prejudice to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or any third perſon leave it undone: he is bound in charity and compaſſion to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:172774:17"/>his Brothers Soul (for whom Chriſt died) and for the avoiding of Scandal, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge himſelf in the exerciſe of his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty for that time ſo far, as rather to ſuffer ſome inconvenience himſelf by the not doing of it, then by the doing of it, to cauſe his Brother to offend. The very caſe which is ſo often, ſo earneſtly, and ſo largely inſiſted upon by Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.13-21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1-3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7-13: and 9.12, 15, 19-22: and 10. 23-33. Here the Rule is, <hi>Do nothing, that may be reaſonably forborn, whereat Scandal will be taken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 The laſt way is, when a man doth ſomething before another, which it is not only lawful, but (according to the exigency of preſent circumſtances) <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> very behoofefull, and even <hi>(prudentially)</hi> neceſſary for him to do: but foreſeeth that the other will be very like to make an ill uſe of it, and take encouragement thereby to commit Sin, if he be not withall exceeding carefull, as much as poſſibly in him lieth, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Scandal that might be taken thereat. For, <hi>Qui non prohibet peccare cum poteſt, jubet.</hi> In ſuch caſe, the bare
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172774:18"/>neglect of his Brother, and the not uſing his uttermoſt endeavour to prevent the evil that might enſue, maketh him guilty: Upon which conſideration ſtandeth the equity of that judicial Law given to the Jewes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.33, 34. which ordereth, That in caſe a man dig a Pit or Well, for the uſe of his Family, and looking no further then his own conveniency, put no Cover upon it, but leave it open, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it happeneth, his Neighbours Beaſt to fall thereinto and periſh. The owner of the Pit is to make it good, in as much as he was the occaſioner of that loſs unto his Neighbour; which he might and ought to have prevented. Here the Rule is, <hi>Order the doing of that, which may not well be left undone, in ſuch ſort, that no Scandal (ſo far as you can help it) may be taken thereat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To apply this, The thing now under debate (the action propoſed to preſent enquiry) is, <hi>The Laying aſide of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Book enjoyned by Law, and uſing inſtead thereof, ſome other Form of Church Service of our own deviſing.</hi> And the Enquiry concerning it is, <hi>Whether it may be done with a good Conſcience, in regard
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172774:18"/>of the Scandal that is given, (or at least) may be taken thereat; yea or no?</hi> Now for as much as in this Enquiry we take it for granted, that the thing to be done is not in its own nature and ſimply evil, but rather (in this ſtate of affairs) prudentially neceſſary; and that they who make ſcruple at it upon the point of Scandal, have not the leaſt intention of drawing either the Laws into contempt, or their Brethren into Sin by their example: It is manifeſt that three of the now mentioned caſes, with the ſeveral Rules to each of them appending are not pertinent to the preſent enquiry. But ſince the laſt of the four only proves to be our caſe; we have therefore no more to do for the ſetling of our Judgments, the quieting of our Conſciences, and the regulating of our practiſe in this affair, then to conſider well what the Rule in that caſe given, obligeth us unto. Which is, not <hi>to leave the action undone,</hi> for the danger of Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, (which beſides the inconveniencies formerly mentioned, would but ſtart new Queſtions, and thoſe beget more, to the multiplying of unneceſſary ſcruples <hi>in infinitum:</hi>) but <hi>to order the doing of it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172774:19"/>ſo,</hi> that (if it were poſſible) no Scandal at all might enſue thereupon, or at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe not by our default, through our careleſs or undiſcreet managery thereof. Even as the <hi>Jew</hi> that ſtood in need to ſink a Pit for the ſervice of his Houſe or Grounds, was not, for fear his Neighbors Beaſt ſhould fall into it, and be drowned, bound by the Law to forbear the making of it; but only to provide a ſufficient Cover for it, when he he had made it. The thing then in this caſe, is not to be left undone, when it ſo much behoveth us to do it: but the action to be carried on (for the manner of doing, and in all reſpects and circumſtances thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing) with ſo much clearneſs, tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, moderation and wiſdom (to our beſt underſtandings) that the neceſſity of our ſo doing, with the true cauſe thereof, may appear to the world, to the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of thoſe that are willing to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it; and that ſuch perſons as would be willing to make uſe of our example to do the ſame thing, where there is not the like cauſe of neceſſity, may do it upon their own ſcore, and not be able to vouch our practiſe for their excuſe. Which how
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172774:19"/>it may be beſt done for particular dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, every charitable and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious man muſt ask his own diſcretion: Some general hints tending thereunto, I ſhall lay down in anſwering the next Objection (where they will fall in again not unproperly) and ſo ſtop two Gaps with one Buſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>3 <hi>SCHISM.</hi> Object. 3.</head>
               <p>The laſt <hi>Objection</hi> is that of SCHISM. The <hi>Object<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs</hi> hold all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as have oppoſed againſt either Liturgie or Church-government, as they were by Law eſtabliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us within this Realm, for no better then <hi>Schiſmaticks:</hi> and truly I ſhall not much gainſay it: But then they argue. That for them to do the ſame thing in the publick worſhip of God, that Schiſmaticks do, and for the doing whereof eſpecially it is that they juſtly account them Schiſmaticks; would (as they conceive) involve them in the Schiſm alſo, as parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172774:20"/>thereof in ſome degree with the other; and their Conſciences alſo would from <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.22. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them, either of Hypocriſie in allowing that in themſelves, and in their own practice, which they condemn in others, or of unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs in judging others as Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, for doing but the ſame thing which they can allow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to practice. For all that ſuch perſons as they call Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks do in this matter of the Church Service, is but to leave out the Churches Prayers, and to put in their own. Or ſay, this ſhould not make them really guilty of the Schiſm they ſo much deteſt; yet would ſuch their ſymbolizing with them ſeem (at leaſt) a kind of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy complyance with them, more then could well become the ſimplicity of a Chriſtian, (much leſs of a Miniſter of the Goſpel,) whoſe duty it is to ſhun even the leaſt appearance of evil, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.22. Beſides that by ſo doing, they ſhould but confirm thoſe men in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172774:20"/>their Schiſmatical Principles and Practiſe.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Objection</hi> hath three Branches. To the firſt whereof I oppoſe the old ſaying, <hi>Duo cum faciunt idem non eſt idem.</hi> Which although ſpoken quite to another purpoſe, yet it is capable of ſuch a ſenſe as will very well fit our preſent purpoſe alſo. I anſwer therefore in ſhort, That to do the ſame thing that Schiſmaticks do (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in times of confuſion, and untill things can be reduced into better order, and when men are neceſſitated thereunto, to prevent greater miſchiefs,) doth not <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily</hi> inferr a partaking with them in Schiſm: no nor ſo much as <hi>probably,</hi> unleſs it may appear, upon probable preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions otherwiſe, that it is done out of the ſame Schiſmatical Spirit, and upon ſuch Schiſmatical Principles as theirs are.</p>
               <p>The other two Branches; (<hi>viz.</hi> That of ſeeming compliance with Schiſmaticks; and that, of the ill uſe they may make of it, to confirm them in their Schiſm) do upon the matter fall in upon the aforeſaid point of Scandal; and are in effect but the ſame Objection, only put into a new
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:172774:21"/>Dreſs: and ſo have received their anſwer already. And the only remedy againſt both theſe fears (as well that of Scandal, as this of Schiſm) is the ſame which was there preſcribed: even to give aſſurance to all men, by our carriage and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour therein, that we do not lay aſide the Common Prayer of our own accord, or out of any diſlike thereof; neither in contempt of our rightfull Governours, or of the Laws; nor out of any baſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with the times, or other unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſecular <hi>own-ends;</hi> nor out of any Schiſmatical Principles, Seditious Deſign, or innovating Humour: but meerly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced thereunto by ſuch a neceſſity as we cannot otherwiſe avoid, in order to the glory of God, and the publick good: for the preſervation of our Families, our Flocks, and our Function: and that with the good leave and allowance (as we have great reaſon to believe) of ſuch as have power to diſpence with us and the Laws in that behalf: This if we ſhall do <hi>bona fide,</hi> and with our utmoſt endeavours, in ſingleneſs of Heart, and with godly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion; perhaps it will not be enough to prevent, either the cenſures of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:172774:21"/>and inconſiderable perſons, or the ill uſe that may be made of our example, through the ignorance or negligence of ſome; <hi>(ſcandalum puſillorum;)</hi> or through the perverſeneſs and malice of other ſome (<hi>ſcandalum Phariſaeorum,</hi> as the Schools term them:) But aſſuredly it will be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in the ſight of God, and in the witneſs of our own Hearts, and to the Conſciences of charitable and conſidering men, to acquit us clearly of all guilt either of Scandal or Schiſm in the leaſt degree.</p>
               <p>Which we may probably do, by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving theſe enſuing (and ſuch other like) general directions: (the liberty of uſing ſuch meet accommodations, as the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in particular caſes ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, ever more allowed and reſerved,) <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 If we ſhall decline the company and ſociety of known Schiſmaticks, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing frequently and familiarly with them, or more then the neceſſary affairs of Life, and the rules of Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and common Civility will require: Eſpecially not to give countenance to their Church Aſſemblies by our preſence among them, if we can avoid it.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:172774:22"/>
               <p n="2">2 If we ſhall retain as well in common Diſcourſe, as in our Sermons, and the holy Offices of the Church, the old Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical and Eccleſiaſtical terms and forms of ſpeech which have been generally received and uſed in the Churches of Chriſt, which our people are well acquainted with, and are wholſom and ſignificant: And not follow our <hi>new Maſters</hi> in that uncouth affected garb of ſpeech, or canting lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage rather (if I may ſo call it,) which they have of late time taken up, as the ſignal diſtinctive and characteriſtical note of that, which (in that their new Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) they call the <hi>Godly Party,</hi> or the <hi>Communion of Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 If in officiating we repeat not only the Lords Prayer, the Creed, the ten Commandements; and ſuch other paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in the Common Prayer Book, as (being the very words of Scripture) no man can except againſt: but ſo much alſo of the old Liturgie beſides, in the very words and ſyllables of the Book as we think the Miniſters of State in thoſe parts where we live, will ſuffer, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory before whom we officiate wil bear; ſith the Officers in all parts of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:172774:22"/>Land are not alike ſtrict, nor the People in all Pariſhes alike diſaffected in this reſpect.</p>
               <p n="4">4 If where we muſt of neceſſity vary from the words, we yet follow the order of the Book in the main parts of the Holy Offices; retaining the ſubſtance of the Prayers, and embelliſhing thoſe of our own making, which we ſubſtitute into the place of thoſe we leave out, with phraſes and paſſages taken out of the Book in other places.</p>
               <p n="5">5 If where we cannot ſafely mention the particulars expreſſed in the Book, as namely <hi>for the King,</hi> the <hi>Queen,</hi> the <hi>Royal Progeny, and the Biſhops,</hi> we ſhall yet uſe in our Prayers ſome ſuch general terms and other intimations deviſed for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as may ſufficiently convey to the underſtandings of the people, what our intentions are therein, and yet not be ſufficient to fetch us within compaſs of the <hi>Ordinance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 If we ſhall in our Sermons take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, now and then, where it may be pertinent, either to diſcover the weakneſs of the <hi>Puritane</hi> Principles and Tenents to the People; or to ſhew out of ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172774:23"/>and expreſſions in the Common Prayer Book, the conſonancy of thoſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations we have raiſed from the Text with the Judgement of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> or to juſtifie ſuch particular paſſages in the Letany, Collects and other parts of our Liturgie, as have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly quarrell'd at by <hi>Presbyterians, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, Anabaptiſts</hi> and others, by what Name and Title ſoever they be called, of the <hi>Puritan Sectaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus I have freely acquainted you, both with my <hi>Practiſe</hi> and <hi>Judgment,</hi> in the point propoſed in your Friend's Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: How I ſhall be able to ſatisfie his or your Judgement in what I have written I know not; However I have ſatisfied both your deſire and his in writing, and ſhall reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Brother and Servant in the Lord.</signed>
                  <date>Novemb. 12. 1652.</date>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
